<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Blessedness, or, God and the world weighted in the balances of the sanctuary and the world found too light preached in a sermon at Paule, before the Right Honourable the Lord Major, Aldermen, and commonalty of the city of London, on a thanksgiving-day, for the prosperity of our navy in a conflict with the Spaniard, October 17, 1656 / by Francis Raworth ...</title>
            <author>Raworth, Francis, d. 1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12213288</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12213288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 924:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Blessedness, or, God and the world weighted in the balances of the sanctuary and the world found too light preached in a sermon at Paule, before the Right Honourable the Lord Major, Aldermen, and commonalty of the city of London, on a thanksgiving-day, for the prosperity of our navy in a conflict with the Spaniard, October 17, 1656 / by Francis Raworth ...</title>
                  <author>Raworth, Francis, d. 1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 60, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Maxcy, for John Rothwell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CLXIV --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56350:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56350:1"/>
            <p>BLESSEDNESS, OR, GOD and the WORLD Weighed in the <hi>BALANCES</hi> OF THE SANCTUARY AND THE <hi>World found too light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached in a Sermon at <hi>Pauls,</hi> before the Right Honorable the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London,</hi> on a <hi>Thanksgiving</hi>-Day, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of our Navy in a conflict with the <hi>Spaniard, October</hi> 17. 1656.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Francis Raworth, <hi>Teacher to the Church at</hi> Shore-ditch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Maxcy,</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> at the <hi>Fountain</hi> in Goldſmiths-Row in Cheap-ſide, 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56350:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56350:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>ROBERT TITCHBURNE</hi> LORD MAjOR, And the Right Worſhipful the ALDERMEN of the City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable, and Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT cannot be denyed, but that our greateſt happineſs in this world is, That we have liberty to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the world to come; yet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſo unhappy are men, as that they little ponder upon their future Crown, and little conſider of their preſent race; but either they vainly
<pb facs="tcp:56350:3"/>
miſ-ſpend their time (to allude to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor) in gathering Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle ſhells, in heaping together the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs; or in a more degenerous way, in a baſe drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery for the luſts of the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>The Profeſsion of Chriſtianity la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreth under two <hi>Extreams;</hi> ſome pretend to an <hi>Anticipation</hi> or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Heaven, and would fain perſwade us that there is no ſtate of Glory after this life: Theſe men, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their preſent Triumphs, are under great Temptations; and in a ſober ſenſe, are rather beſides their wits, then above Gods Inſtitutions.</p>
            <p>Others charge the faithful Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Religion with uſurpation againſt God, with <hi>Antedating</hi> the ſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:56350:3"/>
Perfection, as if they did confound the diſtinction between the Church Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant and Militant: No, ſay they, Purity and Holineſs are our aim on earth, but our poſſeſsion onely in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Theſe Senſualiſts may learn, that the great change of man is made in this world, and onely confirmed in the next; <hi>the Tribunal Bar Regenerates no man,</hi> but publiquely and finally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitteth the Regenerate: Heaven muſt firſt enter into us, before we can enter into Heaven; though the perfection of Purity be onely in Heaven, yet the principle of Purity is to be had on Earth: He that dies a ſinner, ſhall never riſe a Saint: He that by the Love of the Brethren ſhoots not the gulf here, ſhall never paſs from death
<pb facs="tcp:56350:4"/>
to life hereafter: He that hath not God to be his Lord now, ſhall never have the Lord to be his God. Wo be to that man that was born, and is bred, and ſhall be buried in ſin, that goes out of this world in that condition that he came into the world with, happy had he been that he had never been born; happy, if when dead, he never ſhould have had a reſurrection, becauſe he ſhall ariſe, not ſo much to be judged, as to be condemned.</p>
            <p>Nothing is ſo much diſcourſed of as bleſſedneſs, yet nothing ſo little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; ſome place it one thing ſome in another, yet both amiſs; ſome men would be happy, but without communion with God, which is impoſsible: Theſe
<pb facs="tcp:56350:4"/>
ſhould know, That God hath not onely Mines of Braſs, but Mines of Silver and Gold; and that though the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this world be not an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods anger, yet its no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his peculiar love, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt take heed of valuing the good things of Gods foot-ſtool, above the good things of his Throne.</p>
            <p>My work in this Sermon, hath been to give the world its due, both in its white and black ſides: I have weighed the bleſſedneſs of this world and of the next, in the Balances of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and notwithſtanding this world be pondrous in a providential ſenſe, yet comparatively, by the verdict of God himſelf, it is found too light; to which
<pb facs="tcp:56350:5"/>
when you had given a patient hearing, you were pleaſed by your order to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune its publication: I have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied your requeſt, and my prayers to God are, That becauſe it is a ſubject of the higheſt nature, that it may have the deeper Impreſsion on your hearts: That as God hath lifted you up into the ſeat of Honor, ſo you may lift up that God with Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: That as you have publick Opportunities to do good, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain Prophanation, and diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance Error, ſo you may have hearts ſuitable to your Opportunities. That as God hath thrown into your laps the outward <hi>Happineſſe</hi> of this World, ſo you may prize the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, and ſet a greater Eſtimate
<pb facs="tcp:56350:5"/>
on the light of his Countenance, the leaſt beam whereof is worth ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Worlds.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors, and the Churches Servant in the Goſpel,</hi> Francis Raworth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:56350:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56350:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 144.</hi> ult.</bibl>
                  <p>Happy is that people that is in ſuch a caſe; yea, Happy is the people whoſe God is the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoever the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> (whoſe Character is, <hi>A man after Gods own heart</hi>) doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, he performs it cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and heartily: If he be in a gratulatory vein, and fall to the praiſes of God, he cannot nullifie and debaſe man too low with him; <hi>He is but vanity, and his days are but as a ſhadow,</hi> not worthy to be taken notice of, <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4. And he cannot magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and advance the Lord too high; <hi>He is his Goodneſs, his Fortreſs, his Tower, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, and his Shield:</hi> If he be in a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſture, he is ſo pathetical and powerful, as if God, <hi>q. d.</hi> could not deny him audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: <hi>Bow the Heavens, O Lord, and come down, ſend thine hand from above, and deliver
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56350:7"/>
me out of great waters;</hi> I, and with ſuch a majeſty and life, as if he had the key of Gods Armory to open it at pleaſure, and to throw out ſwords and flaming fire of wrath againſt the wicked: <hi>Caſt out lightning, and ſcatter them; ſhoot out ſharp arrows, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them,</hi> ver. 5, 6, 7. Finally, If he begin to exalt God, he ſets him out with ſuch beauty and excellency, as no Creature or created comfort can be preferred before, no not poſſibly be weighed in the balance with him; to which purpoſe it is obſervable, that as the maledictions threatned againſt <hi>David,</hi> were preſented by the Prophet under three forms, of <hi>War, Famine, and Peſtilence;</hi> ſo here in the latter part of this Pſalm, the Bleſſings of God are expreſſed under three contraries; againſt the Peſtilence is oppoſed this Petition, <hi>That our ſons may be as Plants grown up in their youth,</hi> ver. 12. Againſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>That our Garners may be full, afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all manner of ſtore,</hi> ver. 13. Againſt War, <hi>That our oxen may be ſtrong to labor, that there be no breaking in nor going out, that there be no complaining in our ſtreets,</hi> ver. 14. And my Text is an <hi>Epiphonema,</hi> with which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>Happy is that people that is in ſuch a caſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There is a double bleſſedneſs, <hi>ſiniſtra bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56350:7"/>
a <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> of the left hand, a <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs</hi> of this World. And ſecondly, There is <hi>dextra beatitudo,</hi> a right hand <hi>Bleſſedneſs,</hi> a <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> of Grace, of Salvation; This <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> is the aim of men on earth, but the perfect poſſeſſion onely of men in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Accordingly there is a double interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this Text, ſuitable to the double <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> in it; One interpretation propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it by way of competition, <hi>Bleſſed is the people that is in ſuch a caſe;</hi> that is, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are annoyed with the Peſtilence, have proſperity; while others are conſumed by the Famine, have plenty; while others are deſtroyed and harraſſed with Wars, Tumults and Alarums, have peace and quietneſs in their Borders, <hi>ſic aiunt, ferunt:</hi> This is the Popular rumor, this is the onely Language and Dialect of the vulgar: If they can but have theſe things, they think themſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; whatever become of Religion or of their immortal ſouls; but <hi>David</hi> ſtands up as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with this vote and verdict: How now? Is this true <hi>Bleſſedneſs,</hi> to enjoy the ſhell without the kernel, the Ring without the Jewel, to live like a Beaſt, and die like a Dog (and having no portion in God) after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be damned like a Divel? No, no, ſaith the Prophet, this is a falſe Maxime, a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56350:8"/>
man may be thus imaginarily happy, he may have riches, honor, plenty, pleaſures, and the world at will, and yet be really in a miſerable caſe to all eternity: But if you ſpeak of happineſs, I will put you a better caſe, Happy, yea thrice happy is <hi>that people, whoſe God is the Lord;</hi> a notable <hi>Epanortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> and correction of the Opinion of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happineſs. But the ſecond interpretation more probably ſuppoſeth it to be ſpoken by way of ſubordination and compariſon; as if <hi>David</hi> had ſaid, You call poverty, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace miſeries; and you call riches, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor happineſs: Why? let this be granted that there is ſome kinde of felicity in this world, and that it is better to be rich then poor, to be in honor, then in diſgrace: I will not affirm that there is an inconſiſtency &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choherency between a poſſeſſion in this life, and a propriety in the next; let it be ſo, that a people in ſuch a caſe is happy (and ſo it is a <hi>Synchoreſis</hi> or grant) it is true what you ſay, How happy then is that people, that hath not onely peace without, but peace within; that hath a portion in this world, but yet not this world for their portion; that hath a title not onely to the ſtreams and Creatures, but alſo to the Fountian &amp; Creator? yea doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, happy indeed: Well fare that man, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56350:8"/>
Nation, who in this ſenſe have <hi>God to be their Lord;</hi> and farewell the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> The propoſition from hence is, That the greateſt happineſs in this world, is not to have this world to be our happineſs; but in our Worldly happineſs, to have God to be our Lord.</p>
            <p>The truth whereof will the better appear, by ſetting before your eyes, as in a Table, and by weighing as in ſcales, the happineſs of this world, and the happineſs of Gods people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt make an Anatomy of the World, view it, and ſee what it bids towards happineſs, and without offence I preſume I muſt perſonate the moral or meer worldly man, and ſhew you the happineſs of being in his caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let health, ſtrength, and an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or good temper of body appear: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, what is a velvet Pantofle to a diſ-joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed foot; a Velvet Jacket to a broken arm; the moſt delicate vyands to a diſ-eaſed Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach? The world, my Beloved, is like an Hoſpital of diſeaſed Patients; Here ſtands one man crying out of the Tooth-ach, there ſits another tormented with the ſtone; there lies a third diſtracted with the Collick, a fourth wracked with the Gout: And who is there in this great Aſſembly that can ſay, For
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56350:9"/>
my part I know not who you ſpeak to, I feel no diſtemper, I bleſs God I ail nothing; But how many are ready to complain with him that cryed out, 'tis true, God hath ſet his Rain-bow in the Heavens, his mark in the clouds, that the world ſhall not again be drowned with water: But whats that to me, that am like to be drowned preſently? So what is Peace and Tranquillity abroad, when I have a burning fear within my body? what is it to have plenty in the Land, when I have a lingring Conſumption and Feaver in my blood? It is true, there is never a gracious heart, but would of the two, rather be a <hi>Lazarus</hi> here, then a <hi>Dives</hi> hereafter; rather (if God put it to his choice) beg his bread on earth, then his water in hell; yet as to this world it is better to fare delicately, then to be a Beggar, to be a <hi>Dives</hi> then a <hi>Lazarus;</hi> for a man to have work for God to do, and to have ability of God to do it, while others groan out their days, and waſte their precious time in languiſhments, for others to have good blood running in their veins, to have their bones, as the Prophet ſpeaks, full of marrow and ſtrength: Who would not think himſelf happy to be <hi>in ſuch a caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, What though a man have health, if he enjoy not his Liberty? I muſt confeſs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56350:9"/>
It is better to be a Gally-ſlave at <hi>Algiere,</hi> then to be a drudge to the Divel; it is better to be a <hi>Cato</hi> in a Priſon, with ſhackels &amp; fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters about ones heels, then a <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the Senate houſe, with a chain of Gold about his neck: Yet how ſweet is freedom, not onely in Conſcience, but of Body? Whom doth it not pity to ſee anothers Body to be a Gaol to his Soul, and his Houſe to be a Priſon to his Body? And who would not give the greateſt ſum, with that Greek Captain (in another ſenſe) to obtain this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.28. When I take a view of our weekly Bills of Mortality in <hi>London,</hi> I finde a report of ſo many dying in one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of a Fever, of ſo many dying in another Pariſh of a Conſumption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when I caſt my eye down to the bottom of the Leaf, ſuſpecting ſtill that I ſhould ſee ſome Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of the Plague, contrarily for theſe 12. moneths and above, I finde there nothing but Ciphers: Ah Lord, how unthankful are we for ſuch a bleſſing! when thou might'ſt as juſtly as ſuddenly, turn our <hi>Ciphers</hi> into <hi>Figures,</hi> cauſe our faces to gather paleneſs, hang our ſtreets with mourning, and make us know what an happineſs health and liberty is, by the doleful and dreadful effects and reſtraint of the Plague and Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56350:10"/>Thirdly, But what a caſe were man in, though he had his health, if he wanted <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Friends?</hi> How comfortable is it in the Marriage ſtate, for a man to have his Table compaſſed about not with Thorns and Bryars, but with Olive-plants, emblems of peace: How much better is it for a man to have ſo many children to call him Father, then to have ſo many pieces of gold to call him Lord? Therefore it is, that when God would give us an Inventory of <hi>Jobs</hi> happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he firſt ſets down his piety, <hi>A man fearing God;</hi> but deſcending to his comforts in this life, he begins with his children before his eſtate: <hi>Item,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>Job</hi> had given him ſo many ſons and daughters, whereas certainly ſome ungodly men count children but Bills of charges; and its an ordinary thing to ſay, ſuch a man hath a fair eſtate, and would be an happy man but that he hath a great charge of children. Man is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, not onely Phyſically in his ſoul, becauſe that dies not being immortal; not onely morally in his name and reputation, if godly, becauſe God hath engaged himſelf to make men afraid to pollute the names of them (who while living feared his name) but alſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, in regard of off-ſpring, a man lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo many Lamps burning behinde him,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56350:10"/>
as he hath children ſurviving; and as it was an Old Teſtament curſe to be barren, and to have no light, ſo alſo for God to put out a mans Lamps, and in that ſenſe, to leave a man no light to follow him: Happy, or Bleſſed am I, ſaid <hi>Leah,</hi> (when <hi>Zilpah</hi> her maid bare <hi>Jacob</hi> another ſon) for the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters will call me Bleſſed; and ſhe called his name <hi>Aſhur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for friendſhip, a Friend is a mans ſecond ſelf, he careth at all times, he is <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeps curarum,</hi> partaker of our care; he is (as <hi>Alexander</hi> was wont to boaſt) the beſt treaſure: We know diſeaſes of ſtoppings and ſuffocations, are the moſt dangerous in the body, and it is not much otherwiſe in the minde: You may take <hi>Sarza</hi> to open the Liver, and Steel to open the Spleen; flour of Sulphur for the Lungs, but no receipt, in a moral ſenſe ſo opens the heart, as a faithful Friend: The Parable of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, but true, <hi>Cor ne edito,</hi> Eat not the heart: Certainly if a man would give it a hard phraſe, thoſe that want friends to open them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to, are Canibals of their own hearts: Two, ſaith the Wiſe-man, are better then one, when one falleth, the other helpeth him up. To have health, and liberty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and friends, is comfortable under
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56350:11"/>
God, and who doth not applaud his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that is in <hi>ſuch a caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Fourthly, What though a man had all theſe Providential favors, if he wanted an Eſtate; though its a thing more honorable to be maſter over his Luſts, then to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a great eſtate; and more glorious for a man to have Grace, Love, and Faith, and Patience in his heart, then ſilver and gold in his purſe; yet who knows not but Money is a Queen, and thoſe that abound in it are Kings upon earth with men; that the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower is a ſervant, I oft a very ſlave to the Lender; that he that hath riches, hath wherewithal to give, which becauſe its an imitation of God, is better then to be on the receiving hand; that it is ſomewhat for a man to be able to defray his charges as he paſſeth out of the world, and when he is dead, <hi>rather to have the Pariſh left to his children, then his children to the Pariſh:</hi> And riches (as the great States-man ſaith) are ſo honorable among wordlings, that its hard to diſtinguiſh between virtue and fortune; for the moſt virtuous, if unproſperous, have been deſpiſed; and the moſt impious, if proſperous, have ever been applauded. It is certain, that its onely the right hand of Chriſt, the light of his countenance that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56350:11"/>
muſt ſave, that muſt imbrace us; yet his left hand may be under our heads, the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of this world may help keep us from murmuring and diſtruſt, they may uphold us: It is not for nothing that God coupleth Poverty and Shame together, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.18. The reaſon whereof may be either, becauſe poverty uſually maketh men aſhamed (though in it ſelf its no more ſhame for a man to be poor then to be honeſt) and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is a temptation to men to do things that are ſhameful; and that <hi>Solomon</hi> intimates to us, that there <hi>is greater danger in extremity of want, then in exceſs of wealth: Give me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>neither poverty nor riches:</hi> Why ſo? <hi>Not riches, leſt I be full and deny thee, and ſay, Who is the Lord?</hi> A deſperate Interogatory indeed! but yet not <hi>poverty neither:</hi> Why ſo? <hi>Leſt I be poor, and ſteal, and take the Name of God in vain:</hi> Mark it, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Riches is Pride, but the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Poverty, is ſacriledge againſt God, and it is a greater ſin to Blaſpheme God, whom we own, then to turn Athieſt and deny him.</p>
            <p>But,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, How can this man be yet happy, if in his wealth he want Honor and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? It is known that our Lord and Maſter loſt his good name, and was miſ-called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56350:12"/>
he loſt his life; and ſure enough there will, to the comfort of the righteous at the laſt day, be a Reſurrection of their Names, as well as of their Bodies: Though it be the affliction of a juſt man to be traduced, yet its the ſin onely of the Traducer; for though we have the command of our ears, yet we have no bridle to reſtrain others tongues, and its an ordinary, yet a royal thing to do well, to hear ill: And let no man be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent that his coat be torn, if his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be whole; yet it muſt be acknowledged a great Bleſſing, though not to be flattered, yet to be well reported of; not onely to have a good conſcience towards God, but a juſt credit before men; and if a man loſe the opinion of being good, though yet he be good, he may be packing out of the world for any advantage of doing good; for though a good conſcience be neceſſary for our own ſalvation, yet a good name is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the ſalvation of others; and though it be the care of men generally, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be thought honeſt then to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt: To covet a milk white name, and to be cryed up and down the world, to have the encomiums of men, There goes a righteous man, there goes a charitable man; yet its an honor for a man to have a pot of oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56350:12"/>
and to have no dead flies in it to make it ſtink, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.1. And a good name is rather to be choſen then great riches, and loving favor rather then ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and gold; though ſuch may not have the <hi>Lord to be their God,</hi> yet hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is he in a moral ſenſe that <hi>is in ſuch a caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly. But how ineſtimable were a man, and ſo a Nation, with all this reſpect, if they ſhould want Dominion and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: It is a promiſe that <hi>Gods People ſhall poſſeſs the Gates of their Enemies,</hi> Gen. 22.17. and that their <hi>Rule ſhall extend from Sea to Sea.</hi> The <hi>Athenians</hi> reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their great Empire to be their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt glory: <hi>Alexander</hi> thought himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy that he had not another World to Conquer: <hi>Caeſar</hi> had rather be King of a Cottage, (he ſo loved Rule) then the ſecond at <hi>Rome:</hi> The King of SPAIN gives for his Arms a Shield, with the Sun riſing and ſetting on it. It is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That he that hath the command of the Sea hath the command of the world, and he that hath the command of the Navy, hath the command of the Sea: Now let us ſuppoſe a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56350:13"/>
Nation to have riches at home, and power abroad; for a Nation to be Admiral of the vaſt Ocean, to wear the victorious Flag, and to bring all others under the Lee, and to ſtrike Sail to them as ſupream, to be inſtrumental hereby to report their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious acts in the world, that all Kingdoms and Crowns ſhould admire and honor them; What Nation that had this opportunity to bridle their Neighbors, and awe their moſt diſtant powers into a reſpect, would not count it their glory and happineſs to be in <hi>ſuch a caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, But what is Wealth, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and Dominion, without Peace? How ſad is it to conſider, that while we contend for an ounce of truth, we loſe a pound of love? that like children in the dark miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking our enemies, we ſtrike our friends that are neareſt us? How many are there with us that have once ſhed their blood together, that now are ready even to ſhed the blood one of another? Hitherto we have in <hi>England</hi> been running ſo far from <hi>Babylon,</hi> that we are building a <hi>Babel;</hi> what one calls truth, another calls error; what one calls order, another names Tyranny and Cruelty; but what if Providence ſhould now confound our confuſions? Hitherto we have, like
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56350:13"/>
               <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, been toſſed up and down upon the waves of publick contentions, and endleſs controverſies; What if Providence ſhould ſend ſome Dove with an Olive-branch of Peace, to give us intelligence that our wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall be aſſwaged, that our ſwords here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall be turned into plow-ſhares, that we ſhall neither ſmite one another with the ſword of the tongue, nor with the tongue of the ſword; that the falling out of Lovers, ſhall be the renewing of love; that if we can't love one another as men of one Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet we ſhall as men of one nature and of one Nation; that though we can't bury all our controverſie, yet we ſhall baniſh all our contention: Suppoſe, my Beloved, the Wolf ſhould now lie down with the Lamb (that he may do, and yet not be turn'd into a Lamb) and the Lyon ſhould eat ſtraw like the Ox, and a little childe ſhould lead them; ſuppoſe that every man ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> under his own Vine and Fig-tree (inſtead of mens longing after their Neighbors Vineyards, like <hi>Ahab</hi>) What if ſound and ſollid know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, even of moral righteouſneſs, ſhould revive amongſt us, and ſhould increaſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſively and intenſively, as waters upon the Sea; and that in <hi>England,</hi> the mountain of the Lord, there ſhould be no deſtroying
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56350:14"/>
thing; that we ſhould rather minde the ſtear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the whole Ship, then the guiding of our particular Cabins; rather conſider the common Principles of Reaſon and Religion, to unite us, then the diſputable Points in Church and State that ſeek to divide us: I believe none among us but would deem this Nation happy if ever it ſhould come to be in ſuch a caſe. But though this be much,</p>
            <p>Yea Eightly, For Governors to be as the Angels of God; for Princes to be Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, to make it their buſineſs to defend the People, and for the People to make it their buſineſs to defend their Princes; For Magiſtrates to paint the Walls of a Nation, and not to pluck up alſo the Foundation; to beautifie a Kingdom with Peace, and to build it alſo with Righteouſneſs, that thoſe in a Nation that have no will to do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſhould have no power to do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice; that the Mountains ſhould bring forth Equity, and the little Hills Peace, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 72.3. That the grand Principle of Nature ſhould univerſally be put into pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice amongſt us, for no man to do to another, but that which he would be content another ſhould do to him; that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56350:14"/>
there ſhould be ſatisfaction given for wrongs done to all parties; that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and compoſure ſhould be of all Injuries, by a ſweet Amneſty or Act of Oblivion; What a Golden Age would ſuch things make? For though Morality be not Grace, nor Juſtice to men Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs before God for Satisfaction; yet what a ſhame is it for People to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Goſpel Light, and yet not to live up to Natural Light? And aſſuredly, I had rather converſe in common dealing with a man that is but a Moraliſt, though he be no Chriſtian, then with a Profeſſor, an high Profeſſor of Chriſtianity, that is not a Moraliſt.</p>
            <p>But if we could imagine a Bleſſedneſs of Health, without permanency, we might call an intermitting Ague a good day without health.</p>
            <p>If a Bleſſedneſs of Plenty, without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manency, we might call one mans ſurfeit in a time of dearth, plenty.</p>
            <p>If Peace a Bleſſedneſs, without perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, we might call a nights ſleep in the midſt of a field of Arms, peace. If Riches without permanency Bleſſedneſs, then a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor might be a landed man, that is condemned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56350:15"/>
and muſt die to morrow: Now ſuppoſe what we there call Bleſſedneſs, ſhould be poſſeſt, not onely by this preſent Generation, but by Providence entailed on our Poſterity, and the ages to come? Whoſe Vote is it not that we might ſee this good? and who hath faith to believe that God will render us thus hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py? Yet were we thus happy, it were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comparable to that happineſs which follows, of having <hi>the Lord to be our God, the Lord God to be our Portion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to take off the vail, and ſhew you the world in its deformed, at leaſt, defective colour, in reſpect of the livelineſs and lovelineſs of their eſtate who have an intereſt in the <hi>God the Lord. Yea happy,</hi> &amp;c. Happy, <hi>Aſhrei.</hi> Happineſs is the ſubject of moſt Books, of all Tongues; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his Ethicks with Happineſs, <hi>David</hi> his Pſalms with Bleſſedneſs; ſo Chriſt himſelf the Goſpel, <hi>Bleſſed are the poor, &amp;c.</hi> It may be noted, That no Grammarian among the Jews could ever tell us what this word <hi>Aſhrei</hi> ſignifies, as no Philoſopher among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles what Happineſs is; ſome place it in one thing, ſome in another; the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> place it in Contemplation; the <hi>Stoicks</hi> in Contemplation and Practice; the <hi>Academicks</hi> in Practice; the <hi>Epicure</hi> ſhot nigheſt the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56350:15"/>
mark (however time hath repreſented them) they placed it in the delight that did ariſe from virtuous Actions. Some Criticks ſay <hi>Aſhrei</hi> is an Adverb, and ſignifies Happily; others rather conclude it a Subſtantive, and that P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ural or Dual, and ſo its to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Bleſſedneſſes: And the reaſon why a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious man is ſo called, may be either becauſe his happineſs is a Catholick happineſs: God is not a partial or fragmentary, but a full and perfect good; as all the Lines meet in the Centre, ſo all the happineſſes that are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the Creature, centre in God. Or ſecondly, Becauſe ſuch an ones happineſs is not onely in the Preſent, but alſo in the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Tenſe; he is happy (its true) here, but imperfectly, his greateſt happineſs is yet to come; here indeed happineſs enters into him, but hereafter he ſhall enter into happineſs. The Moraliſt ſpeaks at a great rate, when he ſaith, Call no man happy that hath a great Eſtate, but him that lives up to the Preſcript of Reaſon and Law; <hi>He that ſees no man with whom he would change his condition, he that loſeth that he cares not to enjoy, and enjoys that he can't loſe:</hi> And in a ſpiritual ſenſe he onely is ſuch a man whoſe God is the Lord: Methinks the words are here repreſented as <hi>Antiphanys,</hi> Dialogue-wiſe, The world
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56350:16"/>
begins, Happy is he whoſe Sons grow like Olive plants, yea ſaith <hi>David,</hi> whoſe God is the Lord; the World ſucceeds, Happy is he whoſe Oxen are ſtrong to labor, and that Nation whoſe ſtreets knows no complaining; yea, ſaith <hi>David, whoſe God is the Lord;</hi> ſtill that is the note of a gracious heart, as he reſcribed back nothing but King of <hi>France,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> King of <hi>France;</hi> and why happy ſuch a man above a worldling.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He that hath outward happineſs in the world, may not have a title to the Lord; but he that hath God to be his Lord hath a title, a ſpiritual title to the World: The Corinthians were ready to quarrel about their properties; I <hi>am of one from Paul,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>I am from Apollo,</hi> ſaid another; tuſh, ſaid a third, I care neither for <hi>Paul</hi> nor <hi>Apollo,</hi> give me <hi>Cephas, I am for Cephas:</hi> The Apoſtle rounds them in the ear, what ſaith he, Is Chriſt divided? will you contend for a part? All men are gain, not onely <hi>Paul, Apollo, Cephas,</hi> but <hi>all things, life, death, things preſent, and things to come;</hi> But by what tenure? Why? Becauſe <hi>Chriſt is gain:</hi> When we loſt our Title to God, we loſt our comfortable title to the Creatures, and no wonder the Creature rebels againſt us, ſince we have rebell'd againſt the Creator: The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56350:16"/>
Creatures may juſtly ſay to unregenerate men, that hunt after, and dig for happineſs in them; I ſay, Honors, Riches, Pleaſures, may ſay to ſuch, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did to <hi>Saul, Why come ye to us, ſince God is departed from you?</hi> He is a Rebel that harboreth him whom the King hath Proclaimed a Traytor: And what comfort can that ſoul have, to lay his head in the boſome of any Creature, when God himſelf hath turned his back on him? But he that hath a new title to God, hath a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter title to outward comforts, he holds them in <hi>capite:</hi> God hath provided for him a Kingdom, and therefore doth not grudge him crums? How ſweet are thoſe mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſels of bread, that by Faith are dipt in Chriſts blood? not that property comes by Grace, but it is cleared up by Grace: Many a man hath an Eſtate, and a childe of God enjoys the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it: The worldly man may ſay, This houſe, this childe is mine by Creature right; a Saint ſaith, Theſe are alſo mine by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant right; but you may have all worldly happineſs and not be happy.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſecondly, Grace claims <hi>a title to all the Ordinances of God:</hi> Preaching is thy Chariot, to bring the Lord down to thee: Prayer and Meditation, are wings to carry thy ſoul up to God. It is generally belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56350:17"/>
and without ſcruple among the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that the viſible, and not the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, is the prime and proper ſubject for the diſpenſation of Goſpel Seals, but his title to them that hath a right to Chriſt, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable: <hi>He that can ſay the body and blood of Chriſt is his, may challenge and claim the Bread and Wine that ſignifie thoſe as his:</hi> He that hath right to the Pearl, hath right to the Casket: He that is marryed to the King of Glory, ought not upon any pretences whatſoever, to be kept out of the Preſence Chamber, and from prayer, while others ſtand like ſtrangers without doors knocking, and ſpeaking to God at a diſtance, as ſlaves to a maſter, you have freedom to enter into the Palace of Heaven, and cry, <hi>Abba,</hi> Father: The Ordinances are the glory of a Nation, and where ever God goes, his Ordinances go too, and where ere they reſide and abide, he abides too.</p>
            <p>My Beloved, God and his Inſtitutions go and come from and to a Nation together; as its the honor of a Nation to ſay, <hi>Jehovah-Niſſi,</hi> The Lord is our Banner, in a Military ſenſe for God to fight for us; ſo a greater for others to ſay of any Nation, <hi>Jehovah-Shammah,</hi> The Lord is there, in an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical ſenſe: The Ordinances are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56350:17"/>
of the ſoul, they are not as ſome new Anti-ſcripturiſts calumniate, the Grave wherein Chriſt lies, but the Throne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he ſits as King of the Church; and we were better loſe our evidences for our Lands, then part with the ſeals of the Goſpel: Is it <hi>then a ſmall matter to have liberty to tread in Gods courts, to ſit under the tree of Life and dew of Heaven? to have commerce with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to have communion with the Lord of Glory; when thou art hungry, to have freedom to run to Gods Houſe for Bread; when thou art di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted and troubled with doubts of thy Faith, thy ſalvation, to have recourſe, with</hi> David, <hi>to Gods Sanctuary for reſolution, and that by thy title to the Lord, as thy Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou haſt moreover a propriety in all his Providences; his Providences are thine for thy ſatisfaction; if thou wanteſt enlightning, he is thy Sun; if defending, he is thy ſhield; if a Nation be fearful, he is a wall of fire without; if fainting, he is a well of water within: They may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out many things, but we have the Broad-Seal of Heaven for it that they ſhall want no good thing: Thou art in trouble, and if thy Friend could but ſee thee, How happy? God is therefore Omniſcient: Thou art weak, if thy Friend could help thee? God is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56350:18"/>
Omnipotent, <hi>El Shaddai,</hi> All-ſufficient: If thou art weak, he hath a ſhoulder to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thee; if feeble, a boſom to warm and cheriſh thee: He that hath him that is all, hath all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For thy ſecurity, and that 1. To ſuſtain thee: <hi>If thou goeſt into the water, I will be with thee; if into the fire, Ile be with thee,</hi> ſaid God, <hi>q. d.</hi> If thou burn, Ile burn too; if thou drown, Ile drown too: Hence it was that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſafe in the Red-ſea, and the three children ſecure in the Furnace: God may caſt his childe down, and ſo his Nation, yet not caſt them away; he often breaks your hearts, that he may not break your backs. 2. To order all for thee: The Devil may turn Cordials into poyſon, but providence turns thoſe poyſons into Cordials again: God hath his faireſt ends in our fouleſt ways, when temptations have ſucked our corrupt blood away, thoſe Leeches ſhall be taken off; when you are provoked to ſtorm at God, and quarrel with the ſeeming inequality of his ways, are ready to judge his preſent carriage to your ſouls, inconſiſtent with the hopes of election paſt, or future glory: Let deſpair vail, and murmuring be tongue-tyed, and conſider the Lord thinks it better rather to bring order out of theſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56350:18"/>
ſpiritual diſorders, then not to ſuffer thoſe diſorders to be at all: <hi>Its eaſier for vain man to wrangle with the Almighty, and to ſet up in his pride an Anti-Providence in the world, then rightly to diſcern what God is a doing; we neglect to conſider his way which lies open, and no wonder then we are hampered in finding out his ends, which are ſecret:</hi> Its ſufficient, though God for the preſent ſeem to ſcrible to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eye, yet he will, before he hath done, make his Copy fair: Though the building of <hi>Sion</hi> ſeem confuſed, here lies a beam, there an heap of morter, there unhewn ſtones, yet all things in the end ſhall ſerve this great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect: God hath not more glory now, then we ſhall have good (according to our capacity) hereafter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. Gods houſe may be ſtormed, but it ſhall not be ſhattered; <hi>Sion</hi> like a bottle may be dipt, but it ſhall not be drowned; who dare invade that Nation where God is Pilot, or levy an army againſt that <hi>people whoſe God is the Lord?</hi> For,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, All the Promiſes of God are thine, both firſt for this life: I profeſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, though we ſlightly overlook the Oracles of God: Yet as <hi>there is not one c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand we could miſs, we ſtand in need of ſo much holineſs; ſo there's not one promiſe (though there be thouſands there we could miſs) we ſtand in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56350:19"/>
need of ſo much comfort:</hi> And moreover, there is as much reallity in the promiſes of your God, as there is of formality in the promiſes of men; what men ſpeak falſly, God ſpeaks faithfully: And if any poor ſoul ſay, If God be mine, why then is not comfort and peace mine? Can a man have God to be his Lord, and yet be tormented with ſo many doubts, ſcruples as I am? Yes, your comfort is not always ſo much as your title (your title is to Chriſt, to peace of Conſcience, to a full and perfect joy in the Spirit, but your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort may be little) but yet your title is always more then your actual comfort: The reaſon why you are perplexed in your conſciences, is not becauſe you have relation to God, or becauſe their's no ſatisfaction for you in the Bible, but becauſe you want a mouth to ſuck the breaſt of Conſolation, and an hand of Faith to reach the Pearl of Price: <hi>God always hath a promiſe for your Faith, but you have not always Faith for a promiſe.</hi> Special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the promiſes are yours,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Perſeverance of your Graces: I fear, ſaith a Believer, I ſhall one day fall by the hand of this <hi>Saul,</hi> of this luſt; no, ſaith God, The houſe of <hi>David</hi> ſhall grow ſtronger and ſtronger, and the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> weaker and weaker: But though I depart not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56350:19"/>
from God, yet God may depart from me; he may give me a Bill of Divorce, and recal my ſenſe of his Love, and the teſtimonies of his Grace: No, ſaith God, <hi>I will be your God, and I will not depart from you:</hi> The truth is, our Faith could not keep us, unleſs the power of God kept our Faith: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>We are kept by Faith,</hi> but it is alſo <hi>through the power of God to ſalvation:</hi> You ſay you may fail, becauſe Gods promiſes are your conditions, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member withal, your conditions are Gods promiſes, he bids you make you a new heart, that you may ſee your weakneſs, and his faithfulneſs; therefore he ſaith, <hi>Ile take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your ſtony heart, &amp;c.</hi> God is on both ſides the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> and though the evidence of a Believer may be blurred and blot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, yet the Seal remains on, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver broken off: Whatever Doctrines ſome vent againſt the immutability of ſpecial Love, yet we may eaſily know by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or rather, I confeſs, by Scripture, That <hi>God hath other ways to correct his children, then by caſting them out of his Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To pardon infirmities and ſins: God hath an hook to fetch in your wandrings, and a breſt to take in your weakneſſes: Chriſt hath righteouſneſs againſt your unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56350:20"/>
blood to waſh our tears: Your Coyn, though it have ſome allay, yet if it have the right ſtamp, that ſhall not hinder its currency in Heaven: If you bring your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the touch-ſtone, God will ne'r bring them to the Balance: O how happy are they, that though the world ſee it dirty under their feet, can themſelves at that time ſee it fair above head! That when riches, and health, and friends fail them, and they can't ſay, we have cloathes to cover us, or food to refreſh us; that can yet ſay, Bleſſed be God we are not miſerable, for we have the promiſes, the honey-combs of ſweetneſs ſtill by us. And though you have but little in poſſeſſion, yet,</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the future you have riches in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: Is he an Infidel that will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his Family, and will God neglect his own? Shall ever any be able to write <hi>Infidel on Gods door?</hi> He is a Father, and as he now lays out by Providence, ſo by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe he hath laid up for his Children: Will communion with God in his Ordinances ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you? if not, you have a promiſe of communion with God above Ordinances, where the Sun ſhan't ſhine by day, or the Moon by night, for the Lamb ſhall be your light: <hi>God</hi> hath already prepared Heaven
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56350:20"/>
for his, and wonder not at the croſſes, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of this life, for they are our Fathers foils and fires to prepare his for Heaven: Earth is the place where you ſeek happineſs; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is the place where you ſhall finde it. A great part of our Eſtates lies in Bills and Bonds, and it is kept for you in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hands till you come to Heaven: You may look for much, and often turn over your Evidences, I mean your promiſes, and ſee your future riches, but you'l never know all your Eſtate till you come to enjoy it, and then you ſhall have as much peace, as much glory in poſſeſſion, as now you have in hopes: If therefore the promiſe of a Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> after a Wilderneſs; the promiſe of an Harbor, after ſtorms and tempeſts, will make you happy, you can't be miſerable; and if the ſenſe of the joy of Heaven, if the Contemplation and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atifical Viſion of <hi>God;</hi> if the actual par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of Glory, with the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the beauty and face of Chriſt himſelf can take away your miſeries, then you ſhall be happy, for the Lord ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt of ſcruple, then manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be <hi>your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56350:21"/>Fifthly, You have a <hi>title to all the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God,</hi> his Providential care is yours: the eye is the tendereſt part of the body, the apple is the tendereſt part of the eye; now you all are as dear to God as the <hi>apple of his eye,</hi> Zech. 1.8. A man will rather endure a thump on the back, then a touch on the eye: When you are aſleep, God is awake; when you are in a fit of temptation, careleſs of his glory, yet even then he is careful for your ſalvation: <hi>Iſrael</hi> that is kept, may both ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and ſleep; but he that keeps <hi>Iſrael</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſleep, no not ſlumber: God ſo provides for all his children, as if they were but one, and ſo provideth for every ſingle or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar childe, as if he had never another childe to provide for in all the world beſides: The Lord hath a Book to write down your names, and a bottle to put your tears in. His power likewiſe is yours: the Lord hath not ſo much need of your patience, as you have of his power; and as what the Lord is, he is for you; and as what the Lord hath, he hath for you; ſo what the Lord can do, he will do for you. Though <hi>the promiſe of God be the meaſure of your faith</hi> (and therefore beware in times of tryal, of charging your ſelves for unbelief, when God himſelf poſſibly doth not in that particular command you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56350:21"/>
               <hi>yet your faith is not the meaſure of his power:</hi> The Lord uſually doth for his Church more then they believe, and we muſt believe he can do more for his Church then he doth; nothing but contradiction (to ſpeak re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentially of God) paſſeth omnipotency: Gods people have a double guard, one within them, and that is, The finger of God, the Spirit; another without them, and that is, The arm of God, his Power; a double hold alſo on God, as he hath that double guard on them; <hi>Promiſe</hi> what he will do, <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> what he hath done: As <hi>Sions</hi> cauſe is good, ſo ſhe wants not as good a Champion to maintain it: <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower;</hi> and though the righteous can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſt in a name of Godlineſs, yet they may in the name of God; and therefore in times of trouble they run to it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.10. Lord, may <hi>Syon</hi> ſay, Support under tryals, and deliverance from danger, is an Article of thy Covenant; And will not the Lord be faithful? Are our infirmities many? the Lord our God hath mercy to pardon them: Are our corruptions many? he hath power to ſubdue them: Are our ſins great? he hath love to cover them: What a Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Centre of Attributes are in God! <hi>Righteouſneſs, Holineſs, Wiſdom, Power, Grace,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56350:22"/>
and mercy?</hi> I, every one of theſe Attributes is <hi>God;</hi> and as when <hi>Mithridates</hi> eſpouſed the daughter of a poor laboring man, the <hi>General</hi> to teſtifie the approbation of his choice, ſent the old Father a <hi>Cap full of gold,</hi> with which he being over-joyed, runs up and down the ſtreets ſhewing of it to all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, crying out, <hi>All this is mine:</hi> So may the people of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Promiſes, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, Ordinances, Attributes, Graces, are theirs,</hi> triumphantly ſignifie to the world, All theſe are ours; and that which is more then all this, if more can be, you <hi>whoſe God is the Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Have a <hi>propriety in God himſelf,</hi> in Chriſt himſelf; as <hi>the Lord, when he could ſwear by no greater, ſware by himſelf;</hi> ſo he having no greater thing to give, gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Chriſt, who is the beloved of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Firſt-born of every Creature, he likewiſe is yours, your King to Rule you, your Prieſt to ſatisfie for you, your Prophet to Indoctrinate and teach you; his Death, and Reſurrection, and Interceſſion are yours, not onely for ſignification, but for efficacy: His blood, his precious and pearleſs blood is yours to pardon you; His glorious and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56350:22"/>
ſweet Spirit is yours, to purifie and purge you: And for all things elſe in the World, they are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. But ſhort and <hi>tranſitory:</hi> Riches are well called Moveables, and ere long they will either take their leave of us, or we ſhall certainly take our leaves of them: Honor is but brittle, it is even like <hi>Glaſs,</hi> of which they ſay, when it ſhineth bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt its nigheſt melting: And for the reſt, how uncertain are all things, money for the Thieves, Merchandizes for the Winds, Cattel for the Rot, Buildings for the Fire? The glory of this World is in it ſelf but the Scheme, but the Picture of Happineſs, and it will not ſit ſo long before your eyes, as that you may draw its Picture, its gone before you can ſay 'tis here: But ſuppoſe Worldly happineſs were long, yet,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Its <hi>Inſatisfactory:</hi> Worldly comforts are even like drink to the Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie man, encreaſing thirſt; like Wood to the Fire, enlarging its Flame: The cheſt may be filled with gold, but <hi>God</hi> onely can fill the heart: <hi>Theſe things cannot make you happy,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56350:23"/>
becauſe they are deſired not for themſelves, but for other things;</hi> but the Lord is deſirable not for ſomething elſe beſide himſelf, but onely for himſelf: <hi>Deus propter Deum:</hi> If you have Riches, you may look beyond them and ſee Honors to tempt your eye; if you have Riches and Honors, you may look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them, and ſee moral Wiſdom to tempt your head; if you have all theſe, you may yet look beyond, and ſee health to tempt your heart: And while theſe partial and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect happineſs lay before you, you may look beyond them all, and ſee a neceſſity of ſomething elſe, that is, God to be your God: But <hi>let a man be made an heir of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let a man be adopted into the Family of God, and be able to ſay, The Lord is my God; and I provoke that man to ſay its true, God and Chriſt, and Heaven and Grace are mine, but I want ſomething elſe beſides theſe in the world to make me happy:</hi> Theſe things are not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally good; clothes are but for the back, meat for the belly, muſick for the ears, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the ſmell and eye, &amp;c. but the Lord is a Catholick, a viſcerate and entire good, he is Almighty or All-ſufficient: As a man that hath a minde to ſome particular diſh, can finde all diſhes in that one diſh; as ſuppoſe Patridges, Capons, or Pheaſants: So a childe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56350:23"/>
of God can finde all things in God, riches, honor, pleaſure: The covetous man makes his gold his God, but a gracious heart, ſaith God is my <hi>Gold:</hi> A man may have ſilver, but ſilver ſhall never ſatisfie him without God; but if a man love God, he will ſatisfie him without ſilver: When a poor Beggar is matched to a Royal Prince, ſhe views his Palace, ſhe ſurveys his gardens, and pleaſeth her ſelf in a delightſome proſpect of all his greatneſs and glory, and can ſay, <hi>Theſe are mine, for the Prince himſelf is mine:</hi> So becauſe you have a title to the Fountain, the ſtreams are yours: What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever happineſs is ſcattered here and there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the Creatures, it is all virtually, eminently, and ſuperlatively in God. I read of a couple of Ambaſſadors, the one a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> the other a <hi>Venetian,</hi> and they did both of them extol and prefer the Revenues of their particular Maſters; ſaid the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ambaſſador, My Maſter hath ſo many cheſts of Silver and Gold; alaſs, ſaid the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador, Your Maſters Treaſures have a bottom, but my Maſters Treaſures in the <hi>Indies,</hi> have a Root, a Spring: So may a true Saint ſay to the World, your riches and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts have a leak or limitation; but my Lord Jeſus, his comforts and riches, his Treaſures,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56350:24"/>
have neither Banks nor bottom: <hi>God</hi> is mine, and if he can make me happy I ſhall not be miſerable: This, this my Beloved, is your Inventory for Happineſs, that can ſay, <hi>The Lord is our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to the Application of the Propoſition, and treat with your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in theſe following Deductions or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</p>
            <p>Firſt Concluſion from hence is, a Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that true Opinion that <hi>Gods</hi> people have of the falſe happineſs of the World: Wicked men are <hi>infiliciter felices,</hi> unhappily happy; you <hi>feliciter infelices,</hi> miſerable in your Imagination, but happy really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: You rightly and righteouſly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, that a man may have a gay coat and a feſtered Conſcience; a great Eſtate in his hands, but little or no true comfort in his heart; that though Riches have not ſo much as the wings of a Sparrow in flying to us, yet they, when gotten, make to themſelves wings, and that of an Eagle, to flie away from us: That worldly delights are but as a Snow-ball, which being with much pains heaped up together, melteth preſently if the Sun do but ſhine out: That reſtleſs man, in wreſtling and contending for what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, is but like a childe running up and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56350:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
down in a pleaſant Meadow after a painted Butterfly, which when he hath taken, all the recompence it affords, is, but onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmear his fingers. You ſpeak truly and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when you ſay, That a dram of Grace is worth a pound of Gold; that all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and Creatures in the earth are but meer Ciphers, unleſs God be purpoſed to ſet on the firſt Figure: That while a Diadem ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth light on a Princes head, it may for all that lie heavy enough on his conſcience: That there is no indiviſible connexion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Kingdom on Earth, and a Crown in Heaven: That a man may poſſibly ſwim in a Sea of Pleaſures in this World, and yet ſink into an Ocean of wrath and Brimſtone in the next: That a man may be ſo honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſo rich, ſo glorious, while he lives, that every man may be ready to ſay, There goes an happy man; yet that man, when he dies, for want of a configuration to Chriſt and title to God, may be miſerable to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Could men carry their eſtates beyond the Line of Mortality, and with their money <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee the Angels at laſt day to plead for them, to prevent the Sentence of the Judge of Heaven and Earth; or after that Sentence is pronounced, bribe the flames of Hell-fire to be pitiful towards, and not to prey on or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56350:25"/>
torment them: this were ſomething for worldly happineſs, but when we ſee that there is no advantage, though a man gain the whole world, if yet he loſe his own ſoul; that all theſe ſublunary felicities, are conſiſtent with Gods eternal indignation, that theſe things, neither ſingly nor joyntly; can ſo much as aſſwage grief, put off cares, much leſs adjourn death or prevent Hell, where there is no remiſſion of ſin, no inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of puniſhment; where the pangs of the damned are not onely for the preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, but for the future interminable. <hi>Who would not pray with a gracious heart, Lord let me be rather miſerable for a time (as the world ſpeaks) that I may be happy for ever, then that I ſhould be happy for a ſeaſon onely, and after that miſerable for ever: Lord, though I deſire to be of the number of thoſe Chriſtians that have their hope and expectation in this world, yet deliver me from thoſe worldlings, whoſe entire portion is in this world, is this world,</hi> Pſal. 17.14. Now we are ready to call the proud, happy; to lift up them high in our thoughts, that are lifted up in the world; but when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come to give to every man according to his works, and in flaming fire to render vengeance to them that know him not, on the one hand; and on
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56350:25"/>
the other hand when he ſhall come to make up his Jewels that now are deſpiſed, and to repair their reproaches before God, in the ſight and audience of men and Angels, that now are triumphed over and trampled upon by men: Who would deem himſelf happy at that day, if he be not in their caſe <hi>whoſe God is the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, Deduction: Here we ſee, as in a Looking-glaſs, the <hi>falſe Opinion that worldly men have of true happineſs, or of the ſtate of the godly:</hi> How ready is a wicked man to compaſſionate the children of God? Alas, ſaith he, To what purpoſe are theſe men ſo preciſe and exact? It may be there may be a Judgement day, it may be not; and how miſerable are they to provide for that which no man living ever ſaw, while they neglect that which is obvious to their very ſenſes? Honors are certain, riches are certain, and while they expect their food, they ſtarve; while they pretend after a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they go naked, while they call God Father, they want even the bread of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; Whereas no man is miſerable in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans accompt, but in his own: You may poſſibly ſee a <hi>Joſeph</hi> in Priſon, while <hi>Pharaoh</hi> keeps a Court; a <hi>Job</hi> on a dung-hill, while a <hi>Julian</hi> is on a Throne: You may ſee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56350:26"/>
them poor and reproached, but did they ever tell you they were miſerable; and when they were without Eſtates and reputation, that they wanted them to make them happy? never ſay a childe of God is miſerable, till he ſay ſo of himſelf. A wicked man may have Bleſſings, and yet not be bleſſed; and a childe of God may have curſes (ſtill from men) and yet not be curſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Its obſerved, That men thus varyed their Opinion about happineſs, becauſe they ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the fruition of that whereof they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, would make them happy:</hi> He that was poor, ſaid, If I had but riches, I ſhould be happy; and ſo riches came to be called happineſs: He that was in reproach, ſaid, Oh! If I were but reſpected I ſhould be happy, and ſo reſpect and repute came to be called happineſs: He that was diſeaſed ſaid, If I had my health I ſhould be happy, and ſo health came to be accompted an happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: The natural man is miſtaken in his verdict; the Saint ſaith, I accompt all things loſs and dung for Chriſt; the natural man; I accompt Chriſt loſs and dung for any thing elſe in this life: The Saint ſeeks for happineſs in croſſes, <hi>Job</hi> 5.10. but the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man or Philoſopher will aſſoon ſeek for light in darkneſs, heat in cold, fire in water,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56350:26"/>
ſweetneſs in gall and wormwood, as for comfort in calamities. Hence Chriſt reads a Lecture contrary to nature, Not <hi>bleſſed are</hi> the merry, but the mourners; not the lofty, but the weak; not the Mammoniſt, but the poor in ſpirit, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.3.<note place="margin">Vos editis beatos eſſe pauperes. Ergo ut tanto facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ati, omnia bona vobis adimimus. Juliani ſcomma in Chriſtianos factum.</note> Thoſe eight Beatitudes, are the eight Paradoxes of the world: As Chriſt ſaid, He had bread to eat that his Diſciples knew not of; ſo the Diſciples of Chriſt have an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to enjoy, that the natural man knows not of: The World ſhould conſider, <hi>That a man can never properly be miſerable, till he loſe that which made him happy:</hi> You that call outward things your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, your Greatneſs your happineſs, your Gold and Silver your happineſs; when your greatneſs is abated, and you made little or low before the people, when your Gold and ſilver is cankered or corrupted; when the ſcales turn, and you meet with poverty, your happineſs is gone, you are miſerable: But becauſe the happineſs of a Saint conſiſteth not in theſe things, but in Communion with God, but in the Juſtification of his PERSON, and a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56350:27"/>
title to everlaſting life; therefore whatever you take from him you make him not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, till you can take from him his God, his Juſtification, his everlaſting life, for theſe are the things that make him happy: Suppoſe a man that hath thouſands <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> ſhould loſe a few farthings, his Eſtate ſuffers no loſs, becauſe he hath not ſuffered in, hath not loſt his eſtate: Or take a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller that hath a precious Jewel about him, a Jewel of ineſtimable price; he hath ſome looſe money, ſome ſpending money for his journey in his pockets, but his Jewel is made ſecure in ſome private place about his body; a company of thieves ſurprize him and rob him of ſome few ſhillings, or ſome ſmall pence; do you think this man, when he comes to the next Town, would run up and down the ſtreets like a mad man, and cry, <hi>I am undone, I am undone?</hi> No, becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he hath loſt, he hath kept and not loſt his Jewel: How can a childe of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the loſs of outward things, of friends, of eſtate, while his God and Chriſt, his Pearl of price are ſafe? As he, ſaid a wiſe man, will not pine at his bad fortune, while <hi>Caeſar,</hi> while his Emperor is ſafe: When they have loſt God, then they may juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim they are undone. Even <hi>Plato</hi> could
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56350:27"/>
recommend to the Writers of his age, that they ſhould chracteriſe to poſterity no man to be happy that was wicked, and no man to be miſerable that was good: There is no greater thing on earth then man; there is no greater thing in man then his ſoul; and there is no greater thing in the ſoul of Man then God. 'Twas a vain conceit of that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, who refuſing the name of <hi>Pius,</hi> would be called <hi>Foelix;</hi> but <hi>Scylla,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Foelix,</hi> accompted it not the leaſt part of his happineſs, that <hi>Miletus,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Pius,</hi> was his friend. Piety is the beſt friend to Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, though Felicity, outward Felicity, do not always befriend Piety: <hi>Foelix, Acts</hi> 24.22. thought <hi>Paul</hi> unhappy, but <hi>Paul</hi> knew <hi>Foelix</hi> miſerable; becauſe though he might have a chain of Gold about his neck, he had not a dram of true Grace in his heart, the Lord was not his God.</p>
            <p>Third, Concluſion: This Text rectifies a latent and ſecret error, a raſh ſuſpition, as if a man could not be great and good toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, rich and righteous at the ſame time; as if a man might not have Gold in his cheſt, and yet Grace in his heart. My Beloved, That man is not miſerable that hath a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in this world, but he that hath his Portion in this world, or this world for his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56350:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
portion: And though outward excellencies be not godlineſs, yet a man may have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward excellencies, and yet have godlineſs too; as a wicked man may have ſome ſparks of wrath here, yet the Furnace of wrath is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for hereafter; ſo a child of God ſhall have his inheritance hereafter; yet he may have ſome legacies, ſome largeſſes, ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gifts of Providence here: <hi>Covetouſneſs is not the Attribute of Riches (for all covetous men are not rich ſo all rich men are not covetous) but of the Man:</hi> Though a man cannot ſerve God and Mammon, yet he that hath ſerved Mammon may ſerve God, he may have God and Mammon; I, and through Grace, may ſerve God with his Mammon: Here ſtands a poor man in rags, and for ought we know, he is covetous; there ſits a rich man, a wealthy Alderman, and we truſt charitable: Its notable that God doth indifferently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of the black and white ſides of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: Many times he beſtoweth the good things of this world on evil men, there we have an argument that theſe things are not goodneſs in themſelves, and don't make a man happy; and often he diſpenſeth theſe outward good things on the godly; and then you may ſee <hi>Job,</hi> the richeſt man in the Eaſt, and <hi>Solomon</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Here we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56350:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
have an Argument, that theſe things are not evil in themſelves, and ſo don't conclude a man miſerable that hath them.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle gives a charge to rich men that they be not high minded, but no charge that a poor man become not rich, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. The Prophet tells us, That though here there be a difference between man and man, yet in the bed of the Grave the poor and rich meet together, and God owns himſelf the Maker of them both, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.1. And therefore we finde in the Goſpel, poor <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> in the boſom of wealthy <hi>Abraham;</hi> I, Chriſt himſelf bids us not to throw away our Treaſures, but to lay them up by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying them.</p>
            <p>The Father acquaints us, That one day meeting two men in the ſtreets, the one a Gallant, the other a Beggar, cenſured nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but had this charitable reflection on himſelf, There goes a Beggar, and for ought I know, may better bear his Croſs then I do; and there goes a rich Gallant, and for ought I know, may have a better heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his velvet Jacket then I have. The <hi>Lord gives, and the Lord takes away,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> ſo that Riches are GODS gift, as well as poverty, and for ought I know, you may enjoy your Honour and your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56350:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>graces too, your favor, your lawful favor with men, and the ſmiles of Gods countenance too; you may keep (and ſo to improve them by Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) your wealth, your ſtrength, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and your title to God, and the grace of God too: I know nothing but that you may be rich and happy, if you will be rich and godly:</hi> I don't love to hear a poor man declaim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt riches, and a beggar to ſpit at and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie a Crown: Religion may be the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, but the heart may be deceitful for all that: But for Magiſtrates that are highly advanced, to be lowly minded; for Kings to throw down their Crowns at Chriſts feet, and to ſay, Let him reign (and for ought I know, Chriſt may put them on their heads again) for ſuch learned men as <hi>Paul,</hi> that know the price of Learning, and have known the value of worldly felicities, for theſe to count all nothing for Chriſt, this is to inrich riches and honor, honors indeed.</p>
            <p>Let men beware of diſcontented humors in theſe times: The Fox diſpraiſeth the Grapes he cannot reach; let poor men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of prjudice againſt men becauſe they are rich; and it may be rich men may think better of the poor, and of the Lord our God for their ſakes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56350:29"/>Fourth Corollary: This condemns the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency of thoſe that profeſs themſelves to be the people of the Lord: It is ſtrange to conſider how the wicked many times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelves ſo comfortably, ſo chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, as if they were the children of God; and on the contrary, the children of God carry themſelves ſo melancholily, ſo deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, as if they were wicked men, and had no intereſt in God at all; they rejoyce when they ſhould mourn, and you mourn when you ſhould rejoyce. Chriſtians! Is the Lord contented with you, and is not God ſufficient? Will not you be contented with him? Is the Lord ſatisfied with a <hi>My ſon, give me thy heart,</hi> and are not thou ſatisfied with this, the Lord hath given me his ſpirit? <hi>tolle meum, tolle Deum:</hi> Its remarkable that all the Beatitudes are fixed on unlikely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; to intimate, That the Judgement of this world, and the Judgement of Gods children differ about Bleſſedneſs: Shall that man rejoyce that hath but his Angels of gold to ſmile on him, and wilt thou not rejoyce that haſt the Angels of God, I, the God of Angels to tend on thee? Is not he ſad that hath onely a claim to the dirty and muddy ſtreams of Peace, and outward proſperity, and wilt thou be ſad that haſt a title to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56350:30"/>
Well-head of Comfort, to the Spring and Fountain of Happineſs? Shall he be merry that can but ſay, This mirous Houſe, that Mannor is mine; and wilt thou not be glad, when thou ſaiſt, That this God, the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord of Heaven and Earth is mine? Religion is no melancholy thing, though the Religious may be often melancholy; and what ever worldlings phanſie, though oft the body be ſad, yet the heart of a childe of God keeps Holy-day; and if he be troubled, it is not becauſe he is Religious, becauſe the Lord is his God, but becauſe he is ſo carnal, and doubts of that claim: And ſurely one great reaſon why we are not ſo compoſedly chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough, it is becauſe we are not Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans enough.</p>
            <p>Is God thy Father, Chriſt thy Redeemer, the Spirit thy Comforter; &amp; will not this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thee? Haſt thou ſometimes ſuch triumph of heart, that thou wouldſt not exchange thoſe few ſweet minutes for all the World? and doſt thou live in the longing and thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Death and a Reſurrection, and after them the ſight of Glory, and an immutable and immortal ſtate of Heaven and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where thou ſhalt ſigh and ſorrow no more? And will not theſe hopes relieve thee? <hi>Hath the Goſpel diſappointed thy thoughts?
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56350:30"/>
Didſt thou unadviſedly enter into Covenant with God? Is not there that felicity and favor in Gods preſence, that thou didſt promiſe thy ſelf to finde in him? Wilt thou change portions, and exchange properties with the world? Shall this man have thy pardon of ſin, and thou his rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es? that man thy hopes of Glory, and thou his Lordſhip and Honor? Speak out, what wilt thou take for God, what price for thy ſoul? Will Pleaſure and Paſt-time buy it? Will Riches or Revenues buy it? Are not all theſe things partial and improportionable, to the God of Glory and Centre of all Happineſs? If the World can't come up to thy price, and thou canſt not mend thy market, for ſhame be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied and be at reſt?</hi> If you would credit Chriſtianity, and commend thy God to the loſt world; get comfort in thy conſcience, away with unjuſt ſcruples againſt thy enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled peace; part not with thy priviledge or thy God, till thou canſt meet with better: If you value not your own peace, have an eſtimation of Gods glory.</p>
            <p>What will carnal men ſay? Would you have us part with all for God, when you are ready to part with God for nothing? Why do you exclaim againſt our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and our vain Pleaſures, when you your ſelves do ſeem to count Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56350:31"/>
and Heavenlineſs a burthen? either keep your breath to your ſelves, and reprove us no more, or live up to your intereſt, and to honor your God? How do you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us it is worth the while to ſell all for the Pearl of price, that when we have done ſo, we ſhould think our ſelves miſerable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the bargain? It ſeems rather by the anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and perplexity of your mindes, that you envy our comforts in the world, to which for ſhame you dare not return; and would eſteem it a piece of your happineſs, if we would be miſerable with you for company? But let the world conſider, that a Saints want of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort proceeds not from the inſufficiency of his purchaſe, but from his want of faith to claim it: And let Believers conſider, that as their unbelief is uncomfortable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo it reproacheth God. Hence many have denyed God, and ſo have turned Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, becauſe they could not maintain Gods All-ſufficiency, and live like Epicures: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual diſtruſt of God, is a greater Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in ſome ſenſe, then a total denyal of God; for what greater ſhame, then not to believe him whom we profeſs cannot deceive us, and not to be content with him whom we acknowledge to be All-ſufficient? Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the pooreſt ſoul in all this Congregation,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56350:31"/>
that can but ſay, <hi>God is mine, is happier then if he could ſay, all the Mines of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the Weſt-Indies are mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifth Inference: By way of perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the worldly happy, that they would look after the Lord: Why will you ſeek any longer, <hi>vitam beatam,</hi> a bleſſed life; <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem mortis,</hi> in the Region of death? Pearls in the duſt, and Heaven (compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively) in Hell: Wilt thou periſh for that which ſhall periſh? Doſt thou love Gold ſo well, as to run into Hell fire to fetch it? Thou proclaimeſt thy happineſs becauſe of an healthy Body; and wilt thou be leſs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in having a ſound Conſcience? How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py wert thou, if beſides theſe Rings of gold, thou hadſt but the ineſtimable Jewel, if in thy Terreſtrial and Earthly Paradice, thou hadſt but in the midſt thereof the Tree of Life, Jeſus Chriſt? You ought not to throw away Chriſt when you imbrace the world, neither need you prodigally throw away the world when you embrace Chriſt. <hi>Chriſt and the werld may dwell both in one houſe, though not in one heart:</hi> Be as covetous as thou wilt, be as ambitious as thou wilt; wouldſt thou have earth, wouldſt thou have this World? ſo thou maiſt, and Heaven, and the next too.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56350:32"/>As <hi>Achſah,</hi> when her Father gave her a Portion, deſired a Bleſſing, ſo do thou at Gods hand, and ſay, <hi>Lord, Thou haſt given me the nether ſprings, but I yet want the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſprings; thou haſt given me the Streams, but what are all they without the Fountain? As thou art not content with my things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my ſelf; ſo Lord I have thy Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, thy Comforts and Creatures, but theſe are not thy ſelf; all theſe I may have, and yet be poor, naked, be hopeleſs in this life, and a damn'd wretch to all Eternity.</hi> As the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brings in King <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſitting in his chair of State, with his Nobles attending about him, and environed with all outward glory, in the three years Famine, crying out, What avails all this, if yet the Heavens continue to be Braſs and the earth Iron? So what is it to have Friends &amp; favor, &amp;c. and to have a hard heart, a reprobate minde; for God to frown on me, for to live like a Rebel and Runagate without Chriſt and the Covenant of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe? It is true, you ſhould have ſought the Kingdom of Heaven firſt, and then all things would have been added to you; but yet ſince you have begun with the World for Gods ſake, for your ſouls ſake end with God; you are already in poſſeſſion of temporal Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, will it be any damage to have the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56350:32"/>
of eternal happineſs? Are you jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, leſt as you ſhould gain Chriſt, you ſhould loſe the world, and that as Grace comes into your hearts, that your Eſtates muſt needs go out of your hands? Have there been many, that in the midſt of their outward pomp and ſplender, that yet have cryed out Undone; and that for want of Gods preſence and will, their riches im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh you, their wiſdom make you fools, and their Plaiſter wound you? Can All-ſufficiency it ſelf undoe you? Will ſecurity always bar out wrath? Will your Opinion never alter concerning the World? Will Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt never be precious? Will there not come a time when the favor of God will be more neceſſary there, then this mans favor is now? What will you give for a Chriſt at the laſt day? Will the ſenſe of your paſt joys, kill the then ſtinging worm of conſcience? Do but try what peace of conſcience means after your troubles, how much the Pearl of Price weighs after your worldly experience; and if one ſmile (after true poſſeſſion) of Gods favor, if the leaſt aſſurance of the pardoning ſins, do not out-weigh all things elſe, return to the world and to your luſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Its reported of <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> That one day he opened his minde to his friend <hi>Cyneas,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:56350:33"/>
and told him, If he were but Poſſeſſor of <hi>Italy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> what then, ſaid his friend? Why then if he could but conquer <hi>Africa;</hi> what then <hi>Pyrrhus?</hi> O then if he could but ſubdue <hi>Aſia,</hi> he would be at reſt, and be merry with his friends; ſo you may be now, ſaith <hi>Cyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as,</hi> without all that trouble.</p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, By way of Satisfaction: How ſhall I have evidence in the enjoyment of worldly (happineſs, or) goods, that the <hi>Lord is my God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. If thy Eſtate come to thee by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, Induſtry, or the bounty of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; it is one thing to have what we have be Covenant, another to have it by Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Many can ſay, This Eſtate, this Land is mine, becauſe God is mine; but others have occaſion to ſay, If God had been mine, this had not been mine: It is a currant, but unhappy Proverb in <hi>England, Happy is that childe whoſe Father goes to the Divel;</hi> the meaning of it is, The Son oft comes by a great Eſtate, and the Father ſells his ſoul to get it for him; but better it were, that the eſtate ſhould never come to the children, then that the father ſhould go to the Divel for it, Ah Lord! How ſollicitous are men to adorn the bodies of their children, but how careleſs for their ſouls? How many leave
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56350:33"/>
vaſt Eſtates to their children (there's no hurt in providing for their Families, that's a duty) but this is their miſery, their Oppreſſion and Extortion, which procured them entail the curſe of God on thoſe Eſtates: <hi>Wo be to them, ſays the Prophet,</hi> Iſa. 5.8. <hi>that joyn houſe to houſe, and that lay field to field, till there be no place, &amp;c.</hi> Then <hi>wo be to me,</hi> ſaid a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Extortioner, and to my children.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another evidence of our true enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this world upon a good ground is, when we can ſee God in what we enjoy: The Language of <hi>Eſau</hi> is, <hi>I have enough;</hi> but <hi>Jacobs</hi> Dialect is otherwiſe, <hi>The Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to me;</hi> and that which is remarkable, he ſaith of his children, <hi>Which the Lord hath graciouſly given to me:</hi> One would think <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> were ſpeaking of the pardon of ſin, of the hope of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> or of everlaſting life. Grace ſeems to be the language of the Goſpel, and proper onely to ſpiritual Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; but a gracious heart ſees not onely providence, but Grace in what he hath; he ſees grace in his cat el, grace in his children: The rich fool in the Goſpel talked at a great rate, <hi>I will pull down my barns,</hi> and <hi>I will beſtow my fruits;</hi> all belike was his own, God was not in all, in any of his thoughts: Though we muſt not look on the Creatures
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56350:34"/>
with doting eyes, ſo as too much to admire them; yet we muſt not look away from them with ſhut eyes, ſo as to neglect to ſee God in them: How comfortable is it for the ſoul to ſee the love of God to him in the love of his children, and the protection of God ratified to him in the obedience of his ſervants to him, and the <hi>Image of the King of Glory in graven in all his Coyn,</hi> on all his gold and ſilver?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may know the Lord is our God in the fruition of the world, by the enjoyment of God in them: It is nothing for a man to finde a piece of Parchment, a Deed ſigned and ſealed, unleſs there be Land conveyed in it; ſo the poſſeſſion of a great Eſtate is no Argument of Gods love: You have the Deeds, the Conveyances, the Honor and riches of Gods left hand, but by what title? Evidences (my Beloved) are Evidences to them that have a title: If a man enjoy God in his Goods, he hath a title with his Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, a better title then that the worldling hath: It is a ſuſpitious thing to finde Goods in a mans houſe, and for him not to be able to tell how he came by them. My ſoul, How cameſt thou by thy Eſtate, is it given to thee as to a Son, or as to a ſlave? thou art ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced into high place, but ſince thou art
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56350:34"/>
lifted up, haſt thou lifted up God in thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor? Ah Lord! How many are riſen in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, but forgot that hand that lifted them up, and the ground from whence they came? Are your Eſtates as Looking-glaſſes, to ſee God in, to ſee his wiſdom and care, and load-ſtones, to draw out your love by? Are they wings to make you mount up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or no? If they be not wings, they will be weights to ſink you down to Hell: Do Riches make you charitable? Doth Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor make you humble? Doth your ſtrength make you watchful? Do you not caſt away the Net, now you have got the Fiſh? Are you in ſatisfied when you have the cap full of gold, till you have the kiſs? To allude to the competition of <hi>Cyrus</hi> his two Friends, <hi>Chryſautus</hi> and <hi>Artabarus;</hi> are your turns ſerved of God, and do you turn your backs on God? Are you the better for your goods, and the more in love with the Roſe of <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> for your beauty? Can you bleſs <hi>God</hi> the more for your Bleſſings, and ſay, There was a time I was poor and paſſionate, but as <hi>God</hi> hath given me riches, ſo alſo a thankful heart, as <hi>God</hi> hath encreaſed my ſtore, ſo he hath encreaſed my Faith; and the higher I am, the more holy; the greater, the better? If ſo, we are happy; otherwiſe it were better
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56350:35"/>
we had had leſs of this World, then that like the Moon at the full, we ſhould be more diſtant from the Sun; then that with <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> we ſhould follow the chaſe, be exact Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, or Profeſſors of exactneſs, no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then till we meet with honey. It is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Obſervation of a great Traveller, That notwithſtanding all the Religious pretences of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> That the Indians have brought more of the Spaniards to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their gold, then the Spaniards have brought of the Indians to worſhip their <hi>God;</hi> that is, The Indians have made more Infidels, then the Spaniards have made Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When we imploy our Treaſures for <hi>God,</hi> then we ſpiritually enjoy our Treaſures from <hi>God:</hi> They are not <hi>Goods</hi> to us, if we do not good to others with them: We are too ready to receive the Token, and to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Contents of the Letter that God ſends us. We ſay ſuch a man hath an happy Eſtate, when he hath a great Eſtate; but whatever the Eſtate be, the man is unhappy if he be not charitable: Wherefore <hi>David</hi> giving the Character of a bleſſed man, tells us, <hi>Bleſſed is the man;</hi> What man? not he <hi>that hath riches, but he that conſiders the poor:</hi> Conſider how to beſtow them, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 41.1. Oh that men would conſider they are not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56350:35"/>
maſters of their Eſtates (and it is well if their Eſtates be not maſter over them) but Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards: And the Language of a gracious Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard is, <hi>How ſhall I diſpoſe of my Truſt beſt for my Maſters uſe; where ſhall I finde a naked back, that I may clothe it; an empty belly, that I may fill it; an aged Chriſtian, or Miniſter of God, paſt the labors of their ſpecial Callings, that I may ſuccor and ſupply them.</hi> And it would be a noble enquiry of Magiſtrates, whom <hi>God</hi> makes ſucceſsful againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> how ſhall we conſecrate the gain taken from them to the Lord, for <hi>Sions</hi> good? for the advancement of the Goſpel, and Miniſterial Propagation of Chriſts Kingdom; for the preſervation of Goſpel Ordinances amongſt us, from the Invaſion of Prophaneneſs, and the attempts of Hereſie and Atheiſm? But where are theſe <hi>ubies?</hi> How many are loaden with Bleſſings, and yet load God with Curſes? How do men employ their Eſtates rather againſt, then for God; like water put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the fire, and like clouds hindring the ſight of the Sun? But there is a time a caming, when ye men of the World ſhall ſee that Charity was the beſt Uſury, that a good Eſtate was better then a great Eſtate; when they ſhall take their leave of this World, and the glory thereof; when they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56350:36"/>
ſhall by Death be ſummoned out of this life, and loſe their Eſtates and their Souls toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; how happy ſoever they have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted of by men on earth, yet when they ſhall arrive to that Infelicity and ruine, Who would be in their caſe, <hi>whoſe God is not the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56350:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
